<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-03-21T00:24:58-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Axel Emanuel Casas</title><subtitle>personal description</subtitle><author><name>Axel Casas</name><email>Axel.Casas@ruhr-uni-bochum.de</email></author><entry><title type="html">The Man Who Listened to the Dream of a Bird</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/posts/2025/03/blog-post-2/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Man Who Listened to the Dream of a Bird" /><published>2025-03-20T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-03-20T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/posts/2025/03/blog-post-2</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/posts/2025/03/blog-post-2/">&lt;p&gt;Birds have long captured our fascination. Their iconic flights, vibrant plumage, and diverse melodies inspired culture, poetry, music, science, and engineering. In the last decades, we have also realized that they are &lt;strong&gt;insanely intelligent&lt;/strong&gt;. They are truly &lt;strong&gt;cognitive creatures&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2000, a remarkable discovery was made in zebra finches.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A study published in the prestigious journal &lt;em&gt;Science&lt;/em&gt; analyzed the brain activity of these birds when dreaming. They found that the same brain regions involved in song production were activated (Dave &amp;amp; Margoliash, 2000).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Zebra finches were replaying their songs in what looked like a dream.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Years later, an Argentinian researcher tried to listen to these dreams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the story of &lt;strong&gt;Gabriel Mindlin&lt;/strong&gt;, the man who listened to the dream of a bird.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;zebra-finches-tiny-birds-big-discoveries&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Zebra Finches: Tiny Birds, Big Discoveries&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let us present the protagonists of this story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Zebra finches&lt;/strong&gt; (&lt;em&gt;Taeniopygia guttata&lt;/em&gt;) are small songbirds belonging to the class &lt;em&gt;Aves&lt;/em&gt; and the family &lt;em&gt;Estrildidae&lt;/em&gt;. They are from Australia and are known for their characteristic &lt;strong&gt;black-and-white striped chests&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;orange beaks&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These birds are the &lt;strong&gt;most studied&lt;/strong&gt; in neuroscience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They are crucial for scientific research. Thanks to them, we now know a lot about &lt;strong&gt;vocal learning, social behavior, and brain plasticity&lt;/strong&gt;. Oh, and these birds are &lt;strong&gt;the best non-human animal models for studying human language acquisition&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Male Zebra Finches learn their songs from their fathers.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is much like how &lt;strong&gt;humans learn language&lt;/strong&gt;. They memorize songs during a &lt;strong&gt;sensitive period&lt;/strong&gt; and practice until they master them. Surprisingly, they use &lt;strong&gt;similar brain regions to humans&lt;/strong&gt; responsible for speech.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And wait until you find out &lt;strong&gt;what happens in their brains when they sleep&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;replaying-their-songs-in-their-dreams&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Replaying Their Songs In Their Dreams&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This discovery &lt;strong&gt;revolutionized&lt;/strong&gt; the science of sleep.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Replay&lt;/strong&gt; consists of &lt;strong&gt;replaying neural activity patterns during sleep&lt;/strong&gt;. For example, you may have dreamed about what you did in your day. Well, scientists found that these birds &lt;strong&gt;replay the songs they practiced while awake&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This discovery means that &lt;strong&gt;learning doesn’t stop when we go to sleep&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By replaying the songs they are learning, these birds &lt;strong&gt;solidify the neural pathways of these vocal sequences&lt;/strong&gt;, therefore reinforcing memory. This is &lt;strong&gt;similar&lt;/strong&gt; to how humans replay memories or practice motor skills when sleeping.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this also means these birds &lt;strong&gt;could have subjective experiences&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And Gabriel found a way &lt;strong&gt;to listen to their dreams&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-gabriel-listened-to-the-song-of-a-bird&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How Gabriel Listened to the Song of a Bird&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One day, &lt;strong&gt;Gabriel Mindlin&lt;/strong&gt; received an urgent email from a colleague.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This person was &lt;strong&gt;Amish Dave&lt;/strong&gt;, who discovered &lt;strong&gt;replay in Zebra Finches&lt;/strong&gt;. In this email, he told Gabriel that he had &lt;strong&gt;forgotten to disconnect the recording instruments&lt;/strong&gt; of the bird he was studying. He went to sleep without turning off the instruments!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Amish was studying the &lt;strong&gt;muscle movements in the bird’s throat&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When he went back, the bird was sleeping. But in the data from the registers, he found that the &lt;strong&gt;Zebra Finch was still moving its throat muscles like it was singing&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bird was &lt;strong&gt;sleeping but still moving its throat like singing&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-brilliant-idea&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Brilliant Idea&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Based on this, &lt;strong&gt;Gabriel had a great idea&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He had been studying &lt;strong&gt;the physics and dynamics of vocal production&lt;/strong&gt; for quite some time. Over the years, he designed a &lt;strong&gt;program&lt;/strong&gt; capable of generating &lt;strong&gt;a synthetic version of a sound using throat muscle movement as an input&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He had been doing this &lt;strong&gt;in humans&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But now, he had &lt;strong&gt;data from a sleeping bird&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;“Could I replicate and generate a synthetic sound of this sleeping bird?”&lt;/strong&gt; he thought.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If this worked, he could &lt;strong&gt;literally listen to the dream of a bird&lt;/strong&gt;, as the &lt;strong&gt;muscle movements of the sleeping bird almost perfectly matched those when the bird sings awake&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-first-time-a-human-heard-an-animals-dream&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The First Time a Human Heard an Animal’s Dream&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He used the data provided by Amish and &lt;strong&gt;tried to create a synthetic sound from it&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next morning, he turned on his computer excitedly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He took some coffee and sat down. Next, he put on his earphones and uploaded the &lt;strong&gt;throat muscle data&lt;/strong&gt; to his program. Clicked &lt;strong&gt;play&lt;/strong&gt; and listened.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;He started laughing.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gabriel &lt;strong&gt;did it&lt;/strong&gt;. For the first time in human history, he was &lt;strong&gt;listening to the dream of an animal&lt;/strong&gt;. Happiness overwhelmed his body and senses. He was smiling &lt;strong&gt;face to face in the laboratory&lt;/strong&gt;, speechless, emotionally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everyone looked at him, &lt;strong&gt;wondering what was going on with their director&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-scientific-breakthrough&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A Scientific Breakthrough&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Months later, he and his team published their results in &lt;em&gt;Nature&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A bunch of &lt;strong&gt;physics, dynamic systems, and neuroscience&lt;/strong&gt; made it possible to get into something as &lt;strong&gt;slippery as a dream&lt;/strong&gt;. And in a &lt;strong&gt;non-human animal&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Would it be possible to &lt;strong&gt;see or feel how other animals experience the world&lt;/strong&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Only &lt;strong&gt;science&lt;/strong&gt; will tell us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;animals-are-incredible&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Animals Are Incredible&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They continually amaze us with their &lt;strong&gt;unique colors, behaviors, and the complex ecosystems they inhabit&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In &lt;strong&gt;Cognitive Creatures&lt;/strong&gt;, you will discover their secrets and learn &lt;strong&gt;why they are crucial for our planet&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;some-questions-for-you&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Some Questions for You&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Do you think animals are conscious?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What do you think another animal can dream about?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What animal would you like to learn about?&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;We will write about it!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“With a greater sense of understanding comes a greater sense of wonder.”&lt;/em&gt; — Anil Seth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;-references&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;📚 References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dave, A. S., &amp;amp; Margoliash, D.&lt;/strong&gt; (2000). Song Replay During Sleep and Computational Rules for Sensorimotor Vocal Learning. &lt;em&gt;Science, 290&lt;/em&gt;(5492), 812-816. &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1126/science.290.5492.812&quot;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1126/science.290.5492.812&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Amador, A., Perl, Y., Mindlin, G.&lt;/strong&gt; et al. (2013). Elemental gesture dynamics are encoded by song premotor cortical neurons. &lt;em&gt;Nature, 495&lt;/em&gt;, 59–64. &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1038/nature11967&quot;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1038/nature11967&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>Axel Casas</name><email>Axel.Casas@ruhr-uni-bochum.de</email></author><category term="animals" /><category term="birds" /><category term="dreams" /><category term="sleep" /><summary type="html">Birds have long captured our fascination. Their iconic flights, vibrant plumage, and diverse melodies inspired culture, poetry, music, science, and engineering. In the last decades, we have also realized that they are insanely intelligent. They are truly cognitive creatures.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">An Introduction To The Neuroscience of Consciousness</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/posts/2025/03/an-introduction-to-the-neuroscience-of-consciousness/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="An Introduction To The Neuroscience of Consciousness" /><published>2025-03-19T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-03-19T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/posts/2025/03/blog-post-1</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/posts/2025/03/an-introduction-to-the-neuroscience-of-consciousness/">&lt;p&gt;Consciousness is arguably the biggest mystery of the universe. It is about what it is like to be me, you, or another species. For some, it is about how matter becomes imagination (Tonini &amp;amp; Edelman, 1998). At its core, it is about subjective experiences. This post serves as a friendly introduction to the topic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will focus on the neuroscience of consciousness, its philosophical background, how we study consciousness, and the most prominent theories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enjoy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;before-you-read&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Before You Read&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not an expert on the topic. I have just read tons of papers about it and started to (indirectly) research it in birds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consciousness is a huge topic that cannot be summarized in a single article. This is just a general overview.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can find all the 30 references I used at the bottom and throughout this article.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;table-of-contents&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Table of Contents&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#the-philosophical-problem&quot;&gt;The Philosophical Problem&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#how-neuroscientists-do-research-on-consciousness&quot;&gt;How Neuroscientists Do Research On Consciousness?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#two-theories-of-consciousness&quot;&gt;Two Theories of Consciousness&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#book-recommendations&quot;&gt;Book Recommendations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;1-the-philosophical-problem&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1. The Philosophical Problem&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a long time, consciousness was only a topic for philosophers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, after the pioneering work by Crick &amp;amp; Koch (1990) (who suggested studying the neural correlates of consciousness), consciousness gained significant attention in the scientific community. Since then, many theories have been proposed (for a review, see Seth &amp;amp; Bayne, 2022).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Philosophy, its ideas, and its definitions shape how we do research.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;a--isms&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A. -isms&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;em&gt;Being You: A New Science of Consciousness&lt;/em&gt;, Anil Seth (2021) summarizes the -isms as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Functionalism:&lt;/strong&gt; Consciousness depends on the functions performed by the brain, not on its physical structure.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Materialism:&lt;/strong&gt; Consciousness arises from physical processes in the brain.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dualism:&lt;/strong&gt; Consciousness and physical reality are separate things.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Panpsychism:&lt;/strong&gt; Consciousness is a fundamental property of all matter.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Idealism:&lt;/strong&gt; Consciousness is the primary reality, and the physical world emerges from it.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Illusionism:&lt;/strong&gt; Consciousness is an illusion; it doesn’t exist as we experience it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;b-the-hard-and-the-easy-problems&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;B. The Hard and the Easy Problem(s)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;David Chalmers (1995) argued that consciousness has two problems: the easy ones and the hard one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Easy problems:&lt;/strong&gt; Finding the neural substrates for conscious perception, memory, and other behaviors.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hard problem:&lt;/strong&gt; Explaining how the brain, a physical thing, creates a subjective experience.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nagel (1980) proposed a smart and popular thought experiment to understand this problem:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What is it like to be a bat?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nagel argues that trying to imagine what the bat feels is incorrect. The correct answer is what the bat feels &lt;strong&gt;as a bat&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;c-phenomenological-vs-access-consciousness&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;C. Phenomenological vs. Access Consciousness&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Block (1995) suggested distinguishing different kinds of consciousness:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Access consciousness:&lt;/strong&gt; The sensory information that becomes conscious.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Phenomenal consciousness:&lt;/strong&gt; Pure subjective experience.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;hard problem&lt;/strong&gt; is explaining phenomenal consciousness, while &lt;strong&gt;easy problems&lt;/strong&gt; are related to access consciousness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;d-illusionism&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;D. Illusionism&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Illusionists deny the hard problem entirely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For them, subjective experiences are &lt;strong&gt;not mysterious&lt;/strong&gt;; they are just illusions our brains create (Frankish, 2016).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some influential thinkers in this view are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Daniel Dennett&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Keith Frankish&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2-how-neuroscientists-do-research-on-consciousness&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2. How Neuroscientists Do Research On Consciousness?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How neuroscientists study consciousness depends on &lt;strong&gt;how they define it&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some classic experimental methods include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;1-binocular-rivalry&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1. Binocular Rivalry&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This occurs when each eye is shown a different image simultaneously.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The brain alternates between them, making perception switch from one image to the other.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This helps study the &lt;strong&gt;neural correlates of conscious perception&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;2-priming&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2. Priming&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Priming occurs when exposure to one stimulus influences the response to another.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Often, this happens without conscious awareness.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Neuroscientists use this to explore &lt;strong&gt;unconscious vs. conscious perception&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;3-dreams&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3. Dreams&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dreams provide a &lt;strong&gt;natural state of altered consciousness&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Siclari et al. (2017) used &lt;strong&gt;high-definition EEG&lt;/strong&gt; to predict dream content.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;They identified a &lt;strong&gt;posterior cortical hot zone&lt;/strong&gt; activated when dreaming.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;4-other-methods&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4. Other Methods&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The mirror test&lt;/strong&gt; (Boyle, 2017)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Psychedelics &amp;amp; altered states&lt;/strong&gt; (Yaden et al., 2021)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Metacognition experiments&lt;/strong&gt; (Fleming, 2023)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Illusions, such as the Rubber Hand Illusion&lt;/strong&gt; (Constantini &amp;amp; Haggard, 2007)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;3-two-theories-of-consciousness&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3. Two Theories of Consciousness&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the last decades, two main theories have dominated the field:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;a-integrated-information-theory-iit&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A. Integrated Information Theory (IIT)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First proposed by &lt;strong&gt;Giulio Tononi (2004)&lt;/strong&gt;, IIT suggests that &lt;strong&gt;consciousness is integrated information&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It proposes a way to &lt;strong&gt;measure&lt;/strong&gt; consciousness with &lt;strong&gt;Phi&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It defines &lt;strong&gt;five axioms&lt;/strong&gt; of experience: &lt;strong&gt;intrinsicality, information, integration, exclusion, and composition&lt;/strong&gt; (Albantakis, 2023).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The main problem? &lt;strong&gt;Phi is impossible to falsify&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A fair critique of IIT is found in &lt;strong&gt;Scott Aaronson’s blog&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;br /&gt;
👉 &lt;a href=&quot;https://scottaaronson.blog/?p=1823&quot;&gt;Read the critique&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;b-global-neuronal-workspace-theory-gnwt&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;B. Global Neuronal Workspace Theory (GNWT)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Proposed by &lt;strong&gt;Baars (1997, 2005)&lt;/strong&gt; and later refined by &lt;strong&gt;Dehaene &amp;amp; Naccache (2001)&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Consciousness happens when information enters the “global workspace” of the brain.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;GNWT is &lt;strong&gt;well-supported&lt;/strong&gt; by research (Mashour et al., 2020).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;However, &lt;strong&gt;it focuses on access consciousness&lt;/strong&gt; rather than phenomenal consciousness.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other theories include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Higher Order Theory (HOT)&lt;/strong&gt; (LeDoux &amp;amp; Brown, 2017)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Prefrontal Perceptual Reality Monitoring (PRM)&lt;/strong&gt; (Lau, 2021)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Beast Machine Theory&lt;/strong&gt; (Seth &amp;amp; Tsakiris, 2018)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a &lt;strong&gt;review of 22 theories&lt;/strong&gt;, see &lt;strong&gt;Seth &amp;amp; Bayne (2022).&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;4-book-recommendations&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4. Book Recommendations&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’re interested in learning more, here are some books worth reading:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Being You: A New Science of Consciousness&lt;/em&gt; – &lt;strong&gt;Anil Seth&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Consciousness Explained&lt;/em&gt; – &lt;strong&gt;Daniel Dennett&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Ego Tunnel: The Science of the Mind and the Myth of the Self&lt;/em&gt; – &lt;strong&gt;Thomas Metzinger&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Consciousness and the Brain: Deciphering How the Brain Codes Our Thoughts&lt;/em&gt; – &lt;strong&gt;Stanislas Dehaene&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;A Universe of Consciousness: How Matter Becomes Imagination&lt;/em&gt; – &lt;strong&gt;Giulio Tononi &amp;amp; Gerald Edelman&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;In Consciousness We Trust: The Cognitive Neuroscience of Subjective Experience&lt;/em&gt; – &lt;strong&gt;Hakwan Lau&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-thoughts&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Final Thoughts&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Summarizing consciousness in one article is not fair.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My goal was to provide a &lt;strong&gt;friendly introduction&lt;/strong&gt; to the topic. Philosophical ideas and consciousness theories were &lt;strong&gt;violently summarized&lt;/strong&gt; here. If you are interested, I highly encourage you to read the &lt;strong&gt;cited papers&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope you enjoyed reading this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Albantakis, L., Barbosa, L., Findlay, G., Grasso, M., Haun, A. M., Marshall, W., … &amp;amp; Tononi, G. (2023). Integrated information theory (IIT) 4.0: formulating the properties of phenomenal existence in physical terms. PLoS computational biology, 19(10), e1011465. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1011465&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Baars, B. J. (1997). In the theatre of consciousness. Global workspace theory, a rigorous scientific theory of consciousness. Journal of consciousness Studies, 4(4), 292–309.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Baars, B. J. (2004). Global workspace theory of consciousness: Toward a cognitive neuroscience of human experience. Progress in Brain Research, 150, 45–53. https://doi.org/10.1016/S0079-6123(05)50004-9&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Balduzzi, D., &amp;amp; Tononi, G. (2009). Qualia: the geometry of integrated information. PLoS computational biology, 5(8), e1000462. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000462&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Block, N. (1995). On a confusion about a function of consciousness. Behavioral and brain sciences, 18(2), 227–247.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Boyle, A. (2018). Mirror Self-Recognition and Self-Identification. Philosophy and Phenomenological Research, 97(2), 284–303. https://doi.org/10.1111/phpr.12370&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chalmers, D. J. (1995). Facing up to the problem of consciousness. Journal of consciousness studies, 2(3), 200–219.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Costantini, M., &amp;amp; Haggard, P. (2007). The rubber hand illusion: Sensitivity and reference frame for body ownership. Consciousness and Cognition, 16(2), 229–240. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.concog.2007.01.001&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Crick, F., &amp;amp; Koch, C. (1990, January). Towards a neurobiological theory of consciousness. In Seminars in the Neurosciences (Vol. 2, №263–275, p. 203).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;David B Yaden, Matthew W Johnson, Roland R Griffiths, Manoj K Doss, Albert Garcia-Romeu, Sandeep Nayak, Natalie Gukasyan, Brian N Mathur, Frederick S Barrett, Psychedelics and Consciousness: Distinctions, Demarcations, and Opportunities, International Journal of Neuropsychopharmacology, Volume 24, Issue 8, August 2021, Pages 615–623, https://doi.org/10.1093/ijnp/pyab026&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dehaene, S. (2014). Consciousness and the Brain: Deciphering How the Brain Codes Our Thoughts. Viking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dehaene, S., &amp;amp; Naccache, L. (2001). Towards a cognitive neuroscience of consciousness: Basic evidence and a workspace framework. Cognition, 79(1–2), 1–37. https://doi.org/10.1016/S0010-0277(00)00123-2&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dennett, D. C., &amp;amp; Dennett, D. C. (1993). Consciousness explained. Penguin UK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Edelman, G. M., &amp;amp; Tononi, G. (2013). Consciousness: How matter becomes imagination. Penguin UK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fleming, S. M. (2024). Metacognition and confidence: A review and synthesis. Annual Review of Psychology, 75(1), 241–268. https://doi.org/10.1146/annurev-psych-022423-032425&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Frankish, K. (2016). Illusionism as a theory of consciousness. Journal of Consciousness Studies, 23(11–12), 11–39.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Geukes, S., Huster, R. J., Wollbrink, A., Junghöfer, M., Zwitserlood, P., &amp;amp; Dobel, C. (2013). A Large N400 but No BOLD Effect — Comparing Source Activations of Semantic Priming in Simultaneous EEG-fMRI. PLOS ONE, 8(12), e84029. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0084029&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Koch, C., Massimini, M., Boly, M. et al. Neural correlates of consciousness: progress and problems. Nat Rev Neurosci 17, 307–321 (2016). https://doi.org/10.1038/nrn.2016.22&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lau, H. (2022). In consciousness we trust: The cognitive neuroscience of subjective experience. Oxford University Press.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;LeDoux, J. E., &amp;amp; Brown, R. (2017). A higher-order theory of emotional consciousness. Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, 114(10), E2016-E2025. https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.1619316114&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mashour, G. A., Roelfsema, P., Changeux, J. P., &amp;amp; Dehaene, S. (2020). Conscious processing and the global neuronal workspace hypothesis. Neuron, 105(5), 776–798. 10.1016/j.neuron.2020.01.026&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Metzinger, T. (2010). The ego tunnel: The science of the mind and the myth of the self (Vol. 16). ReadHowYouWant. com.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nagel, Thomas. “11. What Is It Like to Be a Bat?”. Volume I Readings in Philosophy of Psychology, Volume I, edited by Ned Block, Cambridge, MA and London, England: Harvard University Press, 1980, pp. 159–168. https://doi.org/10.4159/harvard.9780674594623.c15&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oizumi, M., Albantakis, L., &amp;amp; Tononi, G. (2014). From the phenomenology to the mechanisms of consciousness: integrated information theory 3.0. PLoS computational biology, 10(5), e1003588. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003588&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Seth, A. (2021). Being you: A new science of consciousness. Penguin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Seth, A. K., &amp;amp; Bayne, T. (2022). Theories of consciousness. Nature Reviews Neuroscience, 23(7), 439–452. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41583-022-00587-4&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Seth, A. K., &amp;amp; Tsakiris, M. (2018). Being a beast machine: The somatic basis of selfhood. Trends in cognitive sciences, 22(11), 969–981. 10.1016/j.tics.2018.08.008&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Siclari, F., Baird, B., Perogamvros, L., Bernardi, G., LaRocque, J. J., Riedner, B., Boly, M., Postle, B. R., &amp;amp; Tononi, G. (2017). The neural correlates of dreaming. Nature Neuroscience, 20(6), 872–878. https://doi.org/10.1038/nn.4545&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tononi, G. An information integration theory of consciousness. BMC Neurosci 5, 42 (2004). https://doi.org/10.1186/1471-2202-5-42&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tong, F., Meng, M., &amp;amp; Blake, R. (2006). Neural bases of binocular rivalry. Trends in Cognitive Sciences, 10(11), 502–511. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tics.2006.09.003&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Axel Casas</name><email>Axel.Casas@ruhr-uni-bochum.de</email></author><category term="consciousness" /><category term="neuroscience" /><category term="philosophy" /><summary type="html">Consciousness is arguably the biggest mystery of the universe. It is about what it is like to be me, you, or another species. For some, it is about how matter becomes imagination (Tonini &amp;amp; Edelman, 1998). At its core, it is about subjective experiences. This post serves as a friendly introduction to the topic.</summary></entry></feed>